JACOB COLVIN

Platform, Site Reliability, and Software Engineer

Cincinnati, Ohio @ me@jacobcolvin.com jacobcolvin.com @0xMacro in colvinjm MacroPower

ABOUT

With over seven years of experience in the tech industry, my expertise lies in Site Reliability Engineering, enriched by a deep focus in Software and Platform Engineering. My passion lies in building robust developer platforms, crafting maintainable infrastructure as code, and architecting systems in a way that is simple and straightforward. My experience as a developer, with a focus on Go and Python, enables my ability to create platforms that are not only reliable, but also enjoyable to use.

EDUCATION

B.S. Information Technology University of Cincinnati - CECH

- 🗖 Aug 2015 April 2020
- · Cybersecurity specialization
- Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS

Infrastructure: AKS K3s Talos Azure Cilium Terraform Ansible Helm Crossplane Cloud Foundry
Development: Go Python FastAPI TypeScript Jsonnet Profiling OpenTelemetry PowerShell Bash Make
Observability: Prometheus Thanos Grafana Jaeger Loki Vector Fluentd OpenTelemetry Datadog
Azure Managed: Databricks Datafactory Postgres Key Vault Storage Account
DevOps/GitOps: FluxCD ArgoCD GitHub Actions Azure DevOps

EXPERIENCE

84.51° / The Kroger Company

Remote / Cincinnati, Ohio

May 2016 - Current

Senior Site Reliability Engineer (Kubernetes)

- ☐ January 2023 Current
- Redesigned large parts of our IaC (Terraform, Flux) for Kubernetes (AKS), reducing manual toil by 200+ hours per year, to support increased scaling demands of new production workloads (driving \$300MM+ operating profit).
- Developed **Python** application for scaffolding template repositories, as well as centralized **Helm charts** and related **GitHub Actions**, which collectively saved developers 3000+ hours during the first year in production.
- Led Datadog cost-saving efforts which reduced spend by over \$400k per year; enforced controls using Terraform.
- Participated in an on-call rotation for our production Kubernetes clusters; ensured compliance with SLAs.
- Empowered developers to efficiently and independently troubleshoot their applications by acting as lead subject-matter expert for observability platforms; headed support and maintenance of all observability tooling, including Datadog, Grafana, Prometheus, Thanos, Jaeger, OpenTelemetry Collectors, and Vector.

Senior Site Reliability Engineer (Observability)

April 2021 – December 2022

- Deployed and supported enterprise observability services/tooling, utilizing Ansible (on-premises) and Flux (Azure Kubernetes), including Grafana, Prometheus, Thanos, Fluentd, Telegraf, and Jaeger.
- Developed Python library to centralize instrumentation for Prometheus metrics, OpenTelemetry tracing, structured logging, and pprof profiling, with support for FastAPI, Databricks notebooks, and more, which both delivered a positive and consistent experience with our observabilitly platforms, and directly saved developers a collective 1000+ hours.
- Led development of multiple Prometheus exporters using Go, utilizing Redis for caching, distributed workers with pub/sub and leader election, CEL for custom rule evaluation, Cue and custom tooling for validation, and Go text templating.
- Rolled out Datadog as a unified logging platform for both Azure and on-premises systems, using Terraform for configuration and Fluentd for log parsing and forwarding; enabled deprecation of multiple disparate logging solutions.
- Created multiple Jsonnet libraries for Prometheus and Alertmanager configuration, saving 100+ hours per year.
- Contributed small fixes to Grafana, Thanos, Jaeger, and other upstream Git repositories.

☐ January 2020 - March 2021

- Created and administered multiple Azure environments using Terraform in Azure DevOps; said environments frequently included resources such as Databricks workspaces, Datafactory instances, Key Vaults, Storage Accounts, and Postgres databases.
- Enhanced our Prometheus ecosystem by adding high-availability and long-term storage via Thanos, thus allowing consumers of Prometheus to track SLOs and KPIs over years instead of days.
- Assisted a mix of seven development and data science teams with Azure migration, Terraform, Grafana dashboards, Prometheus alerts, GitHub Actions, and Azure DevOps pipelines; acted as technical liaison to increase speed and accessibility of support.

ICT Co-op

Versatilist Engineer

May 2016 - December 2019

- Designed a C# API layer over several legacy systems, and a SPA using TypeScript with React, to both assist with support, and improve velocity towards deprecation of legacy systems.
- · Created a Prometheus exporter for SonarQube data, along with corresponding dashboards, rules and alerts, to allow security team to gather relevant KPIs.
- Automated Red Hat Linux VM deployment through ServiceNow, via interactions with Satellite, vCenter, SolarWinds and Ansible.
- Designed a custom web framework using PowerShell and Bootstrap for executing administrative tasks and aggregating events and metrics from many distinct products.
- Automated many miscellaneous tasks using PowerShell, VBA, Bash and PL/SQL in Bash; created and documented Automic workflows with Bash and SAS ODS.
- Interfaced with BOSH and Hadoop to design custom Pivotal Cloud Foundry monitoring solution.

KEY PROJECTS

OmegaGraf

- jacobcolvin.com/OmegaGraf
- An open-source project that seeks to completely automate vCenter monitoring, by orchestrating a small ecosystem of containers, including Telegraf, Prometheus, and Grafana.
- Paper: https://scholar.uc.edu/concern/student_works/jw827c971
- Technologies: Docker, C# / .NET Core, TypeScript, React

Homelab

MacroPower/homelah

- Infrastructure-as-code for my homelab / personal cloud. Defines multiple interconnected Kubernetes clusters, spanning across bare metal (Talos) and multiple Hetzner cloud environments (k3s-on-MicroOS).
- Technologies: Talos, Cilium, ArgoCD, Helm, Jsonnet, Terraform

Prometheus Video Renderer

- MacroPower/prometheus_video_renderer
- Just for fun, completely impractical tool that allows you to encode audio and video as Prometheus metrics.
- https://grafana.com/blog/2021/07/30/how-to-use-grafana-and-prometheus-to-rickroll-your-friends-or-enemies
- Technologies: Go, Jsonnet

Analytics Panel Plugin

MacroPower/macropower-analytics-panel

MacroPower/wakatime_exporter

- Grafana panel plugin that injects JavaScript into dashboards, which reports user session information to a backend Go server, which in turn exports Prometheus metrics for display in (you guessed it) Grafana.
- Over 1MM downloads, featured by Giant Swarm:
- https://www.giantswarm.io/blog/grafana-ception-or-how-we-do-grafana-analytics-giant-swarm
- Technologies: TypeScript, React, Go

Wakatime Exporter

- Prometheus exporter and Grafana dashboards for Wakatime coding statistics.
- Over 100k downloads
- Technologies: Go